this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hello this is Matthew Farwell
for software engineering radio our topic
today was property based tests and we're
talking with Bill Venice bill is
president of our temir incorporated to
provide her skull and consulting
training books and tools
he leads the open source projects for
the Scala test testing library and thus
galactic library for functional
object-oriented programming
he is co-author with Martin Odyssey and
Lex spoon of the book programming in
Scala and here's a community
representative on the Scala centers
advisory board bill welcome to software
engineering radio thank you
so we've had several episodes in the
past where we talk about testing
including episode 283 Alexander tar
lender on developer testing and episode
2 5 6 J fields on working effectively
with unit tests today we will be
concentrating on property based tests so
I think we need to start at the
beginning and just define what is a
property based test Oh a property based
test it's a kind of test where you
specify a higher-level property of your
code something that is supposed to obey
some specification of that behavior it
doesn't really talk about how to test it
just says what the thing is supposed to
do and then the testing tool will
generate examples our data to test that
property with and it does that for you
so you end up specifying tests at a
higher level and it's a little more
concise and then the tool will fill in
the data for you based on the types that
you're better passed into the property
what problem is this sort of testing
trying to solve one thing is that it
helps make your tests more concise
there's less there's usually less code
because when you write traditional tests
which are sometimes called example based
tests you come up with example data for
example if you have a function that
increments an INT and it's supposed to
return one more you might come up with
well let's try zero let's try one let's
try negative one that's right forty-two
that's probably a good one and you know
you come up with examples of data to
pass into that thing and then you check
to make sure each time that it's what
you expect when you pass 42 and you
wanna see 43 whereas with a property you
would just say that what comes back
should be one more than one good what
goes in and then the tool the testing
tool the property based testing tool
would come up with numbers to pass in
and it's gonna try edge conditions like
zero minus one one max intamin int and
then just randomly kind of pick other
numbers so that that makes it more
concise the other thing that it can help
with is you may not think to try max int
and you know there's there's things you
may not think of just you know when
you're when you're in the in the heat of
battle and you're filling in examples in
your test so I'll try this I'll try 42
very well tested but maybe 43 doesn't
work right so it's usually edge
conditions that you forget and that
that's one of the first things these
tests these tools usually try so these
tools are they better at finding edge
conditions or do they just choose an
edge can just try them all oh well it
depends on the tool and so what one tool
like I'm in the scala community so the
main property based testing tool for
Scala Scala check what it does is it it
tries edge conditions more often than
non edge conditions and it has for each
you know well-known type a set of edge
conditions select for string it's a
empty string that's probably the only
edge condition for int it's minus 1 0 1
minute MaxEnt right so for double maybe
it's not a number maybe not because
often things aren't supposed to work
with not a number so things like that is
just kind of
selected for these basic types and then
when you define your own generators of
data for your types you can actually say
well try these more often in in Scala
check-ins so you can come up with your
sort of define your own edge conditions
sort of by saying I want you to test
these values more often than you know
randomly the others okay so do I require
any special frameworks to use property
based tests you were talking about
scarlet check yes
Scala shakers is one tool there's a in
the scala community there's others and
you know other languages usually have
one I think their regional when I heard
of was quick check from Haskell but you
know usually you need a tool because
something's got to generate the data I
mean you could write that yourself but
you be kind of a your back to writing a
lot of code you didn't up writing the
tool so you might as well try to find
one okay so what what does some of the
common use cases for property based
testing well some people just like it
better and they use it for testing what
I found was that there's a couple
differences like one thing that I do
like
I like the test-driven development vibe
of you write a little test make sure it
fails write a bit of code to make it
pass and then you go back and write
another test and when you go back and
forth like that if you like that kind of
development that's you don't end up with
a property you end up with example based
tests so that's one thing what you could
do is after you've done that I suppose
you could say well no I'm now that I've
kind of got my thing working I can sit
back and look at well what is the real
high-level property of this and refactor
it to a property based test if you
wanted to but we usually don't we just
leave the example based test there and
move on but there are times when I think
there are some use cases where an
example based test is easier so one of
them is if you have a reference
implementation of something and you're
you're creating a new implementation you
can write a simple property that says
well for each of these functions on this
thing I'm writing every
implementing it needs to behave the same
as that other one that I know about
that's real easy to write and you know
it's it's a lot easier than writing
example based tests so that that's one
situation so you would use that for
instance if you in a for instance a hash
hash map implementation you could make
sure that your new SuperDuper SuperDuper
quick hash map implementation is had
exactly the same behavior as the old
right the same output okay but hopefully
faster could you give an example of
where properties base testing found a
real bug okay yes what I found was so I
like this idea conceptually so I wrote a
lot of them and what I found is it
either by the time I wrote them or you
know I don't recall ever finding but I
kind of like hard to write them first so
I tend to write example based tests I
get things working and then I would
write some property based tests just to
sort of you know feel more comfortable
and they would never fail for years
because the code was working and and I
it didn't break
but every time I were to run those tests
every single of those property based
tests would try a hundred different ways
to make it fail though that was the
default in Scala check and that takes
time so over the years it was like you
know churning CPUs were using
electricity and you know I was spending
time and these never found any products
so I was kind of wondering Jesus this
really worth it and then lo and behold
after many years it did find one and it
was an inner condition and I'm sorry I
don't remember it was but then I was
like okay well was that worth it I think
it was worth writing the property based
test but what I did in Scala tests so I
do
Scala tests as you mentioned Scala tests
integrates with Scala check is in Scala
says i changed it a fall to try ten
because where you want to try a hundred
is when you're first trying it out but
once the code is working trying ten no
that's not that many but you don't just
run your tests once you're in them over
and over and over and over and over and
so over the course of a day maybe you
try a hundred maybe try 200 and that's
enough because usually that thing
doesn't say
so that's this one change I made was was
to try fewer by default okay can you
give some use cases where even to be
appropriate to use property based
testing so one of the things I think
property based testing might be good for
and this is something I I'm interested
in exploring in the future is they can
take a lot of the they can replace unit
tests like example based unit tests to
to a good extent I think but integration
tests where you're really having a lot
of side effects I I don't not sure that
that fits as well as example based test
where you really like I kind of have a
BDD specification saying when I log in
when the user comes in and they log in I
do this you know that kind of stuff I
think fits I just haven't seen the fit
yet for property based testing how that
intersects or works well with with a
large you know scale integration test
where you're testing all these pieces
together but you can do it but usually
those tests are slow so you don't try
something a hundred times if it takes
you know twenty seconds each time no
that kind of thing
you know I I think it's sometimes hard
to create a property to sometimes it's
hard to say it so in my is what you're
saying
it's difficult to to find a property
that actually applies to it a test into
a system where you have lots of moving
parts in hand it's just if I can't test
a hundred examples quickly then why I'm
not going to test a hundred examples
right so I guess I would like to test
edge conditions and integration test so
that might be useful but where it you
know when what I think spell check does
for examples its default was a hundred
because Haskell's quick check was one
hundred you know they try under things
each time and so you know if you try
calling that increment function a
hundred times that's like you can't tell
it even happened it's over like that but
if you are gonna have to connect to a
real web server that has to connect to a
database each time and you know it's
gonna be slower so you know you could
just you could test things
numbers of times but it still had I just
didn't feel like the the fit was there
and I really liked these specification
style descriptions of integration tests
that are that are really described
around user experience like when the
user comes and does this and then that
happens then the user sees that that's
how you like those tests so you know
saying it's for integration tests for
instance there it's more appropriate to
use example based testing then for I
feel like I have found that it I just
felt that that was a better fit I could
right I mean you can always write a
property where you wrote an example
based this I think that's probably true
it's just you know if it's with
integration test especially because they
take longer
I mean sometimes people have two hour
long integration tests and you don't
have multiply that by 100 okay could you
give me some examples of a property that
you could test with property based
testing I think you know getting me down
like if you write a function remember
function of method just having something
as specifies the behavior the method
like if you I mean nobody has a needs an
increment function but that like that
duh that would work you could just say
you know when I the basically you're
gonna specify that let's find something
more interesting than increment square
root okay so let's say you have wanted
to have a square root function that
takes a double and returns a double but
instead of returning not a number if
it's a negative number it returns what
throws an exception so it's different
than like the on the Java platform you
can call you can get a square root but
if it's if you pass in a negative it's
you get not a number so that's all
you're doing I could specify the
behavior of that that's kind of an
example of a method that has a reference
implementation to Java or the Scala math
function that the square root is going
to richer that's actually the answer I
want unless the input was negative so I
can just write a proper pretty easily
write a property-based test that
generates doubles you say for all
doubles essentially so long as the
double is not negative then
calling my square root method should
return the same double as calling math
square root so that's one property okay
could you do for instance the sorting
algorithm as a base test oh yeah that's
a good one so if I have a new sort well
it's what algorithm a sort method or a
story a something you want to pass to a
to a method that does sort that takes
like a comparator or something or in
skaaland ordering and you want to test
that then you could write a property
again that would be a good one to do
with reference implementation because
after it's sorted it's sorted that
should be the same whether you're using
a fancy fast algorithm that you're just
designing or the existing you don't want
a big loosing ones so you can call your
method you can have let's say you want
to sort lists or sequences you could
have it generate those and it would
generate an empty list of generalists
with a hundred things in it a generated
list with 99 things and all random
things and then you call you pass that
data into your your sort method and then
you pass the same thing into the known
reference implementation of sort uses a
different algorithm and you just say
these two things should you know the
resulting sorted lists or arrays or
whatever they are should be the same as
each other at the end of it okay does
the property always have to be true or
false or can you can you do the
equivalent of fussy matching
oh it's mostly true Oh fuzzy matching I
know that's something I haven't seen
people do before you could do that
essentially what what you can do is
ignore certain input so like if it
generates and that property if it
generates a negative number we're going
back to the square root one if negative
double comes in then you could say well
ignore this one so that's not that's not
fuzzy that's just um that's just cutting
down the number of inputs to the right
domain of the function yes yep that's
not fuzzy but as far as like getting it
to just say 90% of the time this should
be true you'd have to write that
yourself with Scala check as far as I
know okay do you think it would be
useful
possibly I've never needed that but
if you have something that doesn't need
to be right all the time like you could
have something maybe that perhaps you
could use that for if you have an SLA or
something in 95 percent of the time it
needs to be below this value or
something you could maybe test that way
but okay but usually when I think of a
property I tend to think of this is
something that always has to be true
there's a specified behavior and that's
what I express in it it certainly seems
easier if you if it is either always
true or always false yeah if you look on
the internet for examples of property
based testing you get lots of examples
covering things like associativity or
size of sets or size of lists
but which you know seem to be relevant
to seem to be seem to be useful but
aren't generally in the normal use case
of the normal programmer because normal
program is done right sorting algorithms
that don't write hashmaps don't act do
you can you give some examples of non
let's call an algorithmic property based
tests yeah I I guess you're talking
about just examples are from like people
who are designing collection libraries
and things like that those people don't
do exactly well I don't know you can
just pretty much anything you're doing
you could you can use a property to
express it but it's often I mean the
other thing that I I guess maybe this
part of what makes me feel funny about
integration testing with property based
tests is that it's there's a lot of side
effects going on so where it's really a
great fit is when I can just I have a
pure function that I'm testing and I'm
expressing its behavior its its output
is just behave it just depends on its
input and all I have to do is look at
its output so anytime anytime you have a
function like that you could usually
write a property and it would be nice
when you have lots of side effects going
on
you can still test it you just have to
test the side effects in the property
which is starting to feel a little funny
okay so
is what you're saying that property
based test is nice to have it if you
have a function if you have the pure
function but actually capturing a
property for an integration test is hard
because you have all of these side
effects going on it's not that much I
don't think it's harder than reading an
example based test it just feels weird
to me because I feel like I'm not
because the side effects it will take
longer I feel like it's not as clean
what I what I have felt about property
based tests when you look at the
property it's a function it's a function
like for example the one for square root
would be a function that takes doubles
and returns true or false or returns an
assertion like if it's in Scala tests
you usually use an assertion not boolean
but essentially there there's an
assertion of some kind in that as the
results of that property that's it's
it's a function from the input type that
you generate that actually the tool
generates to a true or false
essentially and I really feel like it's
a specification so one of the other
things that I always thought was kind of
intellectually nice but it didn't take
off in in mainstream programming was
designed by contract preconditions and
postconditions that bertrand meyer put
into eiffel and that essentially allowed
you to write assertions about as long as
my input is valid then my output should
be like this so you could imagine you
know an Eiffel if I was writing that
square root method I would have my
precondition with he had a require
clause that said well the you know the
double that's passed in has to be
greater than or equal to zero right
that's your precondition that you write
that in your property and then the post
condition was the rest of the property
which would be okay now I've got a
result and he had a keyword result so
you could like write assertions about
the result that needs to equal and then
I call my reference implementation so
it's it's like an it was kind of like a
way to do property based testing except
it was different in that these were run
as assertions while the program was
running there was no separate like
tests that run against the public API of
the production code is actually part of
the Breton code and you turn it off when
you're really deploying so that didn't
take off and I don't like having
postconditions running with the software
I think most people don't they write
they like those assertions to be in unit
tests we do leave on the precondition
checks in the running software but we
don't I mean it's very rare that people
in practice and in the Java community
the Scala community put post condition
checks in their code they tend to write
unit tests off to the side and put their
assertions there but what a property
what I felt a property did is it it does
capture that specification nosov it like
what you get with the Eifel designed by
contract stuff is it's a snice formal
contract so like you know the you have a
contract in Scala or Java doc if you go
look at the equals method on Java lying
object it's not just documenting it's
actually a contract it says anybody who
implements this method has to do these
things promises to do these things and
so that's a well I don't call it
informal it's pretty clear in its
English text but it's a human language
contract whereas in which you what and I
think those are important but it's kind
of nice that in Eiffel you have this
formal expression of a contract in terms
of code and this is how you can specify
the behavior of the function in code so
what I felt property based testing does
is it it allows you to often not in the
cook in the production code sort of
mixed in a bit off to the side you have
this statement that says this is the
behave you know this specifies formally
the behavior of this function so that
that's what I I like about it and that
especially makes sense for pure
functions I mean just you know you you
can usually specify a pure function with
a property when you have an impure
function with a side-effect it's
sometimes like I just can't think of a
way to specify
with a property you know I can give you
a specific example of that is a iterator
iterator is next in has next method if
you have an iterator in like the Java
iterator it's a mutable interface it's
supposed to like you use these if you
use next it destroys something right and
it's a one-shot so how would you
actually ever specify in a property
formally that when I call this method
what happens because my you time you
call it you've destroyed it and it's
like you can't really do it and okay so
sometimes you can with mutable objects
like if it's immutable collection you
can say when I mutate the collection by
adding something then when I look it up
it should be there you get you can but
sometimes but it's just like once you
once you move away from pure functions
it sometimes gets hard even or maybe
impossible to really formally specify
with code you know with the property
what the contract is okay for coming
back to the properties for a minute
could you explain what a reference
implementation is or a test Oracle I've
heard it called yeah that's that's when
you are implementing something that
already exists in some extent it could
be an interface I think the example you
had earlier mentioned you mentioned
earlier was a new map implementation and
you can just grab a hash map and say
well actually all these methods should
behave the same way I just have a
different performance profile that's why
I'm implementing this map different a
new one but my property can just say
well let's say there's a method size you
can generate data to put in the map you
can put it in the map and then you call
size and you could call the size method
you could probably just count yourself
but you can also compare it with a
reference of implantation let's say it's
a sorted set a new sorted set then it
could you know whatever the order that
the iterator generates elements out of
the implementation you know that's from
the standard library somewhere should
match the order the elements that come
out of your thing and that's so the
reference implementation is just
something you have that you want to
emulate exactly the
behavior of okay so for instance for a
map you could say if I put it in then it
should and I try and do a get from the
map it should work that sort of thing
and you could say okay so if we for the
reference implementation for the map you
could say okay so I want to do a get and
it has exactly the same behaviors to get
on my map okay or something more
complicated like I we are we doing our
website now and we're replicating like
it was written in Java actually it's
written in about four different
architectures starting in 1995 so it
survived a long time and so the newest
one we want to use this play with Scala
and so we are moving the user sign in
and email address changing that kind of
stuff to Scala so we have the new one
the new code and we have the old code
that for the most part we want it to be
the same behavior alright so that
happens now and then it's when you have
that situation where you have something
that exists and something new you can
write a property-based test that would
be an integration test that says okay I
call the website and sign in this way
and I get something back I could go over
there and I should get the same thing or
you have to use it yeah if I had a user
they show up in some list or something
okay
something it's it's it so it's not that
uncommon that you end up redoing
something that there's an example of how
it's supposed to behave and you can just
make a property to compare what I do do
what that does
okay another technique that I've heard
of is Aaron back again yes that's
another I think sweet spot for
properties which is a good one is some
kind of serialization let's say you want
to do JSON serialization for a whole
bunch of types you can have a property
that for any type T it can serialize its
JSON and then deserialize it back and
then you compare the results with the
original for equality and you could say
the property is those things should be
equal or they shouldn't have the same
state or something that is gonna be true
so that you can compare the two that's
where it's okay so that dot round-trip
that's good way
way of putting it that would be ezel any
protocol any any serialization protocol
any yeah you could do it with the
database as well I suppose if you save
an object into the database and then
read it back from the database and it
should be the same object yes okay so
now we've got these wonderful properties
that we set up how do we generate the
data how does the the test framework
generate the data for these properties
okay so I I don't know how they do this
in Python where there aren't static
types to work off of but in Haskell with
quick check what they did is they and
this worked in Scala also essentially
let's say that that going back to that
square root function that I'm gonna
write that's gonna throw an exception
for a negative input what the input to
that function is is double so there is a
generator of double and when you write
your property you write it in terms of
function from double to let's say
boolean right and then in Scala tests
for example if you say for all and then
you just have a function that takes
double and it and then in the in the
body the function in Scala test you
would normally use a an assertion not a
boolean expression but it's the same
kind of thing where you're saying that's
something that should be true then when
that compiles the compiler can see that
well the type the input type of that
function is a double so I'm gonna look
around for an implicit generator of
double or an ass call it's a type class
J no double so so it basically does it
based on type so if you need doubles
it'll generate doubles and it says okay
I know the edge conditions for double if
you need two inch and a double then it's
these three generators right so it
basically looks at the input to the
property function it says well what are
the types there and then it's gonna look
around for a generator of those types so
if one of those is your type all right
some of you invented then there won't be
a generator for it so you're gonna have
to make one for that so you get a
property based test to work so you need
to make a let's say you make a new
a table class or something then you're
going to need a gin generator of tables
of your kind of tables just let me get
this straight
yeah we have a generator there's inbuilt
generators in haskell and scarlet check
which will generate series of integers
for instance yep yep and there's one for
doubles I assume there's one for Strings
as well yes sort of thing can we do more
structured data like can you expand a
bit on the structured data so what the
way you usually make a new generator is
use a four expression in in Scala which
is you take let's say you make a a
person case class in Scala so now you
have a new class that is named it's a
string and in A's it's an int I like to
call I just number my friends so that's
why every name is a string age is an int
and so what I really need is a I need a
person generator what you can do is say
for some age in and then you have an int
generator some well I'd probably name in
a string generator you yield a person
and so you have to say and it combines
them yeah it makes it yeah combines them
and so now it's really concise usually
to write a new generator in Scala but
you do have to do it and it is work
right so it's not like you don't have to
write examples by hand you have to what
you have to write instead is generators
there's a lot of them out of the box for
basic types so for those you kind of get
for free but as soon as you start having
your own properties for your own types
you're gonna have to write a generator
but you can usually compose it out of
other generators that exists and it's
pretty simple so for age you might
actually not want to say for age in inta
generator it's nons you know
pause ins or something like 0 greater
you'd have a generator for just that and
there's a way to to specify that that's
pretty concise also can you limit the
you've said ok it's a positive integer
but you probably want to limit the the
age to
hundred and fifty or something you don't
want to maxint as an age who wouldn't
want MaxEnt as an age but we want it but
it probably it yeah you might want to
put a maxim on there so so Jenner yeah
so what you start with you can say
essentially what Scala tech tries to do
or these death I mean there's not the
only one there's property based testing
tools try to do is make it you know that
there's a lot of generators on the shelf
or at least syntax for the saying things
like I want to int between 0 and 100 50
and you can just write that very
concisely and then you just put that in
your for expression and that's what
you'll get ages from 0 to 150 and names
you might want to have it you might in
your database have a maximum limit on
the size of a name maybe that's 150 or
something so you can limit the number of
characters in the string to a certain
size right you might want to do that as
well
okay but actually if you don't put the
limit in then you discover something
about you might discover something about
your code that you didn't realize so it
you might discover that your your the
thing you were expecting not to be no
doesn't handle nulls correctly that's
right that's a good point so what what I
like to do is I use like if you don't
have a if you're not gonna use a pause
in type for the age in in your person
class then you should probably not just
limit it to pause ants when you're in
your generator just for that reason okay
yeah so that the type of your generator
should match the type of your you target
class yeah you're tired cause except I
just thinking that the problem of that
is then like going back to the double
like passing it a double half the it's
probably gonna generate half negative
numbers and if you generate half
negative numbers these tools will often
give up and I say well I just couldn't
generate if valid ones right they need
so there you might actually have a
generator of positive doubles and have a
different property for making sure that
when a negative
is passed it throws the appropriate
exception okay and similarly you
wouldn't want to use an int generator
for doubles probably that's because
you're missing a lot of numbers between
numbers often in tests you need data
which is context dependent so the data
that you pass into a function depends on
various different things for instance
you were talking about a person so if
you had an address then if that address
if that person lived in the USA then
they would have a zip code and then a
zip code has a set of boundaries but if
they lived in the UK they knew would
have a postcode so you'd have a
different set of data can we can we do
that can we handle that yes that's so
what what you would do there is maybe
after you generate the age in the name
you generate a zip code and then based
on the zip code you would generate a
different kind of address and then you
would yield the big blob of data that
you you want okay that's good I think
when I say generate I mean in your for
expression you would combine them in
that order so that like the thing that
depends on something else shows up after
the thing that it's already been
generated or you know there's a value
there in it'll oh you cannot matter
you're generating listing like this then
you could generate a size of a list and
then generate that the number of items
yeah okay so it strikes me that there's
problem here with a combinatorial
explosion so if you have a particularly
complex structured data then you might
not explore all of the different
varieties of problems that you might
have with that how do we avoid that
yeah we don't unless it's boolean you're
pretty much probably not gonna explore
the whole space I mean the antis 2 to
the 32 right so I don't know how long
it's like if you do hundred at a shot
how many times is it gonna take before
you I've explored all of them so I have
heard people other people actually me
I haven't me that where I caught
something years later and it was
actually there for a long time it just
took a while to hit it
I wish I could remember the exact use
case but that's people have told me
about who have tried Scala check and
they say occasionally I'll not find it
up front but later it'll hit it usually
it finds it pretty soon because usually
it's you know the whole thing is broken
or the are you forgot an edge condition
and it tries those more often so but
every now and then it'll it'll just
because you know the space is big and
you don't explore the whole space you
know you may miss one and it's it's not
a proof it's still a test even though
you're kind of writing it as like a
specification it's not really proving
that it it's not proving that the
implementation obeys the specification
or fulfills it it's just testing that it
does so you may not you know just
because it passes even passes for a year
doesn't mean you don't still have a bug
so these generators are generating data
and sometimes you would get tests where
the tests would fail but then the next
time you run it the tests pass because
it's not using the same data set how
would you avoid that okay there's two
things there one is that the way you
avoid that test feeling in the future is
fix the bug but what you might not have
context for the bookending yeah you
might not remember what it was right so
you want to reproduce it yeah so what uh
that's it's something the tool needs to
help with and I don't know if this
enhancement has gone into Scala check
yet but in Scala tests we have a and in
our 3.2 which is probably gonna be
called for dotto branch we have some
property based testing this native
discolour test and there's a seed print
out the output U of a failed property
based test it will also print out a seed
and the seat was what was used
originally to flow through the random
number generator and get the random data
and what we did is we made sure that
that was reproducible so if you run your
test again and you say - big s or
whatever we used and put in that seed
then you should get the exact same
failure so I think they have maybe they
were wanting to put that at the Scala
check also it's something the tool needs
to do and I don't know yet if
that's in there to reproduce it and they
had to change how random numbers were
generated in Scala check because they
were using Java's random number
generator which really wasn't you
couldn't really reproduce I mean I'm not
sure they had any way that was an
enhancement right so that's that's one
thing the other is that when you print
out a test failure you talk about what
was the input to the function so you
might have a negative negative for you
to let's say negative 42 didn't work we
tell you that oh is negative 42 that's
what caused it the property to fail so
if somehow you couldn't get the test to
fail again you could just go in and pass
negative 42 in by hand and see it you
should be able to okay so you could you
could actually convert that into an
example based test yes and actually
that's that's not a bad thing to do in
Issa's general practice in software
development is you actually find a bug
you write a test it fails because of
that bug before you fix it and then you
leave it there as like well let's have
more clutter that is you know it's like
if that bug ever shows up again then
there's magic do it yeah there will be a
test that fails but you know maybe it's
not worth keeping it around but it's not
I tend to like to do that I write that
test and I leave it there often when
we're talking about property based tests
we talk about shrinkers could you
explain what a shrinker is okay shrinker
is uh something that I'm not sure they
thought of it originally when they did
quick check in Haskell but essentially
what these generators do by default as
they try stuff all over the place so
strings you know think about how you
would generate strings
you don't just generate strings with A
to Z you know you actually just generate
characters all over the Unicode
character set just for the heck of it
and so if you have something with a
bunch of strings in it and then what's I
should have strings B they generate it
they don't wanna go crazy and have them
be you know 64 K long but they'll go up
to a hundred and it gets quite noisy
like some of these outputs saying you
know there could be 10 inputs to your
function and then they're just like huge
crazy-looking things so what what these
tools try to do is
once it finds a failure it tries to
shrink that down to the smallest test
case that causes the same failure
what causes a failure they can't tell if
it's the same one so they'll take those
strings that they know fail and they'll
try smaller ones progressively and then
or the other way that you start small
and go up right
they tries to shrink them down so it'll
try you know if it's an ant it's gonna
try zero
well maybe zero work there so that's a
simpler number so what will happen in
say Scala check scholars check has a
shrink that is or a shrink or shrink
that will kick in once it finds an error
and it'll work on that property and hit
that property a whole bunch of our times
trying to get it to fail with simpler
input and then it shows you the simplest
input it could get the property to fail
with in your output okay so maybe it
starts at zero it goes to 10 20 30 40 50
60 70 80 100 oh it fails it a hundred so
it goes oh I'm going to try 90 again
right try 95 98 99
oh it's 100 yeah it fails right he has
some algorithm that if that's the
shrinker algorithm and you can redefine
that that's based on a type also so you
have a string curve and shrinker of
double shrinker string as you go back
and try the original values that it
tried last time or well I think it
assumes that's gonna fail again I'm not
sure if it actually tries it again I
guess that only works for one input
though doesn't it no the ones that
failed last time it it knows that's what
it's the shaker algorithm knows that
because that's what it uses to decide
what to look at that's mostly smaller
but I don't know that it would try it
again because it would just assume that
it would continue to fail I mean we
already have that one so we don't need
to run that again okay but if you have
two parameters to a function and you try
1 + 1 2 + 2 + 2 + 2 fail but 1 + 1
didn't would it try 1 + 2 or 2 & 1 or
would it just no that's interesting
because there's two shrinkers there the
way that works in Scala so you don't
have a striker of two things you have a
shrink or two shrinkers event
so it depends on how Scala check work so
when we did our shrinking we did it
differently than Scala check one of them
I can't matter which one one of them
started big and went small and the other
one started small and went big but it's
really like you know a lot of times
you're just kind of guessed sounds like
well I don't know I have no idea how to
make this smaller so I'm just gonna try
this and this and this and and like for
an int well we'll try numbers down from
0 to 10 just to see and then we slike
start going larger hops kind of like you
described okay and then you know if it's
getting big like if it's a hundred that
was what failed and we got to you know
fifty and it didn't fail we just say a
hundred you know I think but then that's
a shrink or algorithm and you can
actually redefined that yourself you can
write a shrinker of your type or Straker
event and use that instead if you want
to okay so how would you write how would
you go about writing a shrinker of
structured type say for the person
dress you are given like let's say a
person you're given the person who
failed or guy this person failed so now
you have their age and their name let's
say that's what's in there so what you
might do in your shrinker person is take
a drinker of ant and shrinker of a
string maybe and just reuse those but
essentially what you get is you get that
initial person and you have to produce
in scala check it's a stream of pre
people and it ends at some point so you
just think it's okay try this one try
this one try this one try this one and
that's all you do so you write the tool
you're given the the one that failed and
you just produce a stream of you know
finite stream of other things to
consider which are smaller in some way
simpler in some way and that that's it
okay so in that case you could try as
I've just said you could try reducing
both of them at the same time or just
reducing one of them or reducing the
other right and you're kind of guessing
but actually it works sometimes I think
you'll see crazy failures and then
you'll see simpler ones and it'll say I
shrank three times and it does shrinking
does work and it does make it the output
a little nicer sometimes I guess it's
quite good at working on
lists and collections and maps and intz
I mean a lot of times I who is saying
that these what you get the code working
these tests don't tend to fail for years
so this is usually more when the book
there's actually you're just writing the
thing it doesn't work yet so it really
quickly it finds a bug but with crazy
data well it turns out that bug is there
on simple data that's why I think it
that's when drinking actually helps is
when you're first writing something and
I think just doesn't work and Scala
check found some crazy input that it
failed and then look that's like oh it
actually doesn't fit it feels for empty
string to you know okay so for instance
the size of a list or something like
this it always returns zero in your code
that's the bug so it tries it with a
zero length this mouse works it tries it
with a hundred a list of a thousand
items doesn't work and it shrinks it
down to one a list with one item and
that's much easier that's a great
example and much easier to understand as
well so moving on to other aspects about
property based tests so moving on to
other aspects would you recommend a mix
of property based tests an example basis
and if so which one would you start with
okay so yes I would I would I would
recommend a mix so you see I'm evolving
so what what what I I do like to write
you know a test first and then get you
know a lot of times I'll do that and
when I'm in that means up with example
based tests and I just leave them there
but what I want to do in Scala test is
is formalize this notion of a
specification outside kind of like a
Bertrand Meyer contract but in expressed
as a property separate from the thing
which I think for pure functions is
really nice so I want to try to make
that easier to you know in Scala tests
make that easier to to do so so we'll
see but for integration test like as I
said before I I definitely I literally
think of that as a user from outside the
system using the system from the outside
you write the specification of behavior
that way and it's really just
something even the marketing people can
understand when you come in from the
outside you know this is what happens
this is what's supposed to happen and
that just I think that really clicks
because everybody can understand it and
it's less of a proprietary based testing
but unit tests except for the you know
nice right tests right the code right
that's right the code rhythm
I think unit tests could be more concise
and better if you could actually just
specify these contracts these formal
contracts or specify the behavior with a
property of each pure function at least
okay would you are there any techniques
for dealing with state oh yes
Scala check has a Scala checkbook we
published that has a chapter on state
and he's given a talk I saw Ricard the
guy that did scholarship originaly was
read card Nelson and he gave a talk what
what he suggests there is you make a you
generate almost like a script so you can
make a hierarchy of objects that are
operations and sometimes the operation
has you know some data associated with
it like create user would have a
username or something so you'd make a
create user class that takes a string
name right or and some of them could
just be objects they're just no op I'm
not no ops but like go or stop or
something right so you create you to
find this set of sort of an API that
describes actions and then what you
generate is little scripts you know
little sequences of those objects then
the property can fire at the object and
then look at you know it needs to know
what's supposed to happen but I guess
you didn't might need to generate what
the result it should be but that's
that's how you can do it is like when I
make these and it's randomly generated
what the what the actions are that you
you fire against the mutable thing and
that's nice because you're really trying
all different kinds of common
of actions and then you just check the
you know after all that happens is this
state of this mutable thing in what I
expect it to be okay so you're kind of
modeling it as a as a pure function
almost because you're doing all these
operations you're firing all of these
operations and then you're seeing what
the result is but the result is just a
mutable state of the object yeah I mean
you could basically it's it has to be
predictable otherwise you wouldn't know
what would happen what to check for at
the end so it couldn't be like okay have
27 threads fire things at this I have no
idea what's gonna happen at the end
right it's one thread does just these
things and at the end I know what it is
so what well that means I think is that
it could be rewritten like if that thing
wasn't mutable it was immutable you
could rewrite that as a series of
instead of 20 mutations 20
transformations and then you haven't you
know the output but but in this case
it's you know instead of transforming
things 20 times and throwing away 19
intermediate steps to garbage collection
you just mutate it in place but you
start with something you know he mutated
in place is the only thing doing the
mutation and then it's gonna be you can
expect it should be in this state and
you can test it that way do we need any
specific language features to do
property based testing does do we need
reflection do we need a we need a
functional language do we need a
mutability I think it's like I said I
don't know how they do it in Python they
do it there's there is one but I don't
know how they do generators I guess they
just make a generator and pass it in by
hand I guess that's how you do it in
Python so that's fine so I don't think
so I think the answer is technically no
though what I think is it's really a
nice use case for static types because I
can just write a function that says it
takes these three static types and as
long as there's an implicit generator
you know or generator type class you
know what your languages it just
generates data for you and tests your
can we use property based testing on a
more complex system or should we stick
to small algorithm based modules so that
that could be could we start with small
algorithm bit
based modules or should we start with a
complex system I'd start small because I
actually haven't done big ones I know
people who have and so I just definitely
it's a good fit for pure functions and
you're specifying them from the outside
that's that's like a unit test as far as
you know and no matter how complex it is
if it's pure you can do that but if it's
like a massive enterprise system that's
running you know a company then you you
know you could find things to test I
mean there may be secure I don't know
you could try there's there's use cases
you know where you want to generate a
lot of things like maybe maybe a
penetration testing or something might
just be useful where you you try all
kinds of stuff possibly with smart
generation and let it just hammer away
at it I mean that's that's possible but
um I do I do think the sweet spot is
kind of as an alternative way to do unit
testing for testing things in this small
that's the sweet spot continuing on from
that can we do non-functional testing
such as performance testing using the
same ashley's I haven't done that before
either for with property based tests but
that's where you would want that's what
actually I thought of when you asked me
about fuzzy is that I'm trying to
remember I recently just like last year
we had a client where we were doing
performance testing and I'm trying to
remember how we generated the I mean we
definitely tried a bunch of things how
did we generate that we didn't use I
don't think we used a property based
test we just generated it I mean there's
there's other tools for that like um
there's one from written in Scala called
it's like Gatling this one I mean that's
one tool and there's there's tools just
for performance testing that you might
look at but you could you could I mean
what you can do with with a property and
you know a generator and a property best
testing tool is just hammer away at
something and if what you're interested
in is that it meets an SLA and maybe you
could use it for that okay so you could
use for instance the generator as a
basis for the Gatling yeah or the thing
to send more like hammering away at
something and what I did is I'm actually
remembering now we had
to generate you know a generate customer
IDs customer requests a crate customer
these kinds of things so we had to
generate them somehow we use that random
we use the same random number generator
that we were using in the properties I
don't think it was like a property based
test we just used pieces of it to to do
generation but it wasn't like a property
based test we just probably remember
where we put the data but we recorded we
had these beautiful graphs saying well
here's our performance but it's
different it's a little bit different
then what you do with the property based
testing how does property based testing
impact a team's development process that
is a good question because we know
kickback years ago went around and
talked about test-driven development and
you know write a test first then you
write the code and about it he said
about a third of the people I'm he was
here at gamma here coming out and he
wrote a unit originally together but
they were saying that about a third of
the people are what do they call it test
infected where they get it like oh my
god this is the best way to do things
and they do it another coat of the
people were like kind of I think it's a
good idea but I just I'm lazy or I'm
busy or whatever so they kind of you
know do it when they they're not as
faithful doing TDD and then I'm I've
heard saying this is ridiculous I don't
do this and so that that's sort of you
know for the one-third who really likes
TDD you don't actually get the same
feeling you know you're you you know
it's not the same because I think what
are the things you get about that I mean
you're running example based test it's
not just that it's driving your thought
process you're saying okay well what's
the first little piece of functionality
that I can do what's the smallest one oh
I can do that so let me write that down
in a string that's my test name and then
I read a test it does it it's just this
little thing then I go implement that
you just go back and forth one at a time
so that you you kind of don't get with
property because what you do is you step
back and say okay what is the behavior
of my function the whole thing and you
could write that first but it's it's
just not quite the same process so I
think that's for that one third who
loves it you know maybe they would
prefer to stick with example based tests
to develop but for the other third who
knows maybe they like this better
don't like testing at all it's possible
does it affect you how do you think
about your coat
maybe I mean what I had was a mix right
in my practice I had him I answered a
property-based test just because I
thought well okay I'll I'll stick this
one there to be a good test I don't
think I was thinking in terms of
specification so much and I feel like
that's why I say I want to add something
to Scala test and make that feel more
like I'm actually specifying the
behavior of the function with a property
and and kind of make that more obvious
or something because right now what I
had you know just like I stick a
property-based test in in in the middle
of my example based tests you can do
that in Scala test quite easily but then
it's just like another test it was a
more thorough test and it takes longer
so it's you know I think it I ought to
feel like it'd be nice that Bertrand
Meyer had something with his sign by
contract stuff where you specify it next
to the code the other thing I felt with
testing is that you know your tests just
grow over time and they're kind of all
over the place and it's just not an
obvious mapping between what this tests
and what the code is whereas when you
have a function if you put right there
this formal description of how it's
supposed to behave like in the same file
but it doesn't but not running it the
way I feel did but somehow running it
isn't test that would at least associate
in some way where it's like mapped you
know it's obvious that this is a
specification of that maybe it's not in
the same file but the tool matches them
up or something I think that would be an
improvement because I sort of feel like
these days we write the code and we
write the test over there and they're
just so disconnected sort of that you
know you don't have that feeling of I've
I'm formally defining how this is
supposed to behave and then by the way I
get this test that runs automatically
that you know tries to find it tries to
get to find examples that will cause it
to fail and it's just this that's all I
write I just write this formal
specification which is a lot less code I
think the normal example based is so I
can that like for future directions I
would like to I'm gonna try to explore
that with some enhancements to Scala
test to see if we can get to a place
where
unit testing it kind of comes for free
when you specify formulate the behavior
of a function okay so I think we joined
to a close is there anything else that I
should have asked you well no I think
we've pretty much covered that but think
that's that's the state of it currently
the state of the state of testing is
property by assessing I mean it's not
very popular you don't see a lot of
people using it people who come from the
haskell worldview love it and they use
it a lot and they try to you know
explain it to other people but they tend
to they tend not to use it that much I
don't know why but most people are who
are doing testing to example based
testing these days still still yep one
test is better than notice well i
example pets are better than no test i
guess yeah yes okay well thank you very
much for joining us well thank you for
anything you fought well for software
engineering radio thanks for listening
to SC radio an educational program
brought to you by Triple E software
magazine for more about the podcast
including other episodes visit our
website @ SC - radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
channel at SC radio.com you can also
email us at team @ SC - radio net this
and all other episodes of SU radio is
licensed under Creative Commons license
2.5 thanks for listening